[Music]
foreign
it's good to be back on this live stream
with you all so let us see who all is
there with us tonight uh as you as you
would know I hope that uh today is a uh
it's a live chat show which means I'm
gonna be taking all the questions from
the live chat nothing from the comments
the comments episode will be tomorrow
so this is your opportunity to ask your
best questions and I will try and pick
as many of them as possible so let's see
how who all is there on the live stream
I can see varadh Desai uh yogesh
Leo Messi Herbie on wheels sagnik
Narayan yesterday Alpha Harish anime art
pradeep J as Menor V K IBO hatella
Sharma
foreign
foreign and everybody else so
great to be with you all tonight so
let's take the questions let's begin
with questions from the live stream
let's see uh from the live chat
so go ahead and start asking you
questions and I'll take as many as
possible
go DB says global warming note C route
opens will Indian influence in Indian
Ocean be affected okay so we're talking
about global warming in the north seed
out so what are we talking about we have
to look at the map obviously to
understand this uh the map has
to be brought into the picture where's
the map here's the map
here's a map so we're talking about
global warming North Sea route open so
we're talking about the north the
northern around the North Pole so the
North Pole is somewhere over here as you
can see
the globe is is is rotating around the
north south pole axis North Pole is
somewhere here and typically this this
Arctic ocean is mostly Frozen for much
of the year if not the entire year
definitely seven eight months a year at
least it is frozen because of the cold
temperatures but now with global warming
this sea will be open
uh and and not frozen for um for certain
times of the year in the number of days
it is not frozen will increase which
means that there will be a trade routes
opening up over here and you'll be
people will be able to exploit the
resources that are available in this
region more effectively than before
so does what does this mean for India
does it mean that India's influence in
the Indian Ocean be affected no it will
not be affected because see India is
over here the northern route the
Northern sea the Arctic Ocean is over
here so it's a huge distance and how in
on Earth will it possibly affect India's
ability to influence the Indian Ocean
so uh clearly there's no connection
between these two things uh
obviously India would also like to
participate see if you look at which
country
uh
um is over here it's it's obviously
Russia so much of the coastline of the
Arctic Ocean is uh
it's it's Russian territory and Russia's
exclusive economic zone in Russia's zone
of influence and Russia and India have a
good relationship the Russians have come
out with a new with it with a modified
version of their foreign policy which
they have officially announced which
says that Russia would like to cooperate
deeply with China and India going
forward so these are the two major
Nations that it would it will be
cooperating with extensively so
I'm sure India can also uh participate
in the trading activity and whatever
else resource uh you know looking at the
resources and all that in the North Sea
region in the Arctic Ocean region so it
will help India definitely with Russia's
cooperation but it will not reduce or
affect India's influence in the Indian
Ocean region in any any significant way
whatsoever
all right so that's the first question
that we have taken
uh right let's see uh
other questions
let us see let us see
tell us something about the prakrit
language says ratesh Raj was it a sister
language of Sanskrit is it still spoken
no no no I I know there are lots of
YouTubers and all who and people who
claim that prakrit came before Sanskrit
which is
which is reasonable
it is it is funny and it's not even
funny prakrit is the it was not a single
language first of all prakrit it was a
bunch of languages the prakrits all
right the oldest language that we know
of in the history of humanity is Vedic
or possibly private Sanskrit
linguists talk about a hypothetical
proto-indo-european language well that
language you know so that's what you
will find in all books about Linguistics
in all history textbooks which reference
Linguistics in research papers and
articles
the truth is that the oldest language
that we know of is
Vedic Sanskrit and obviously that
language would have evolved out of
something else which would not be
proto-indo-european it would be pre
Vedic Sanskrit that's what it is so uh
and these bracket languages they emerged
later sometime in the first millennium
BC and uh it's very likely that you know
in the post Vedic Age and before the uh
first millennium BC there was this this
time period the Great mahajanapada era
and all that in which lots of different
languages languages would have been
spoken which would have emerged out of
Sanskrit
languages these were the prakrits and
the prakrits were spoken until the first
Millennium A.D and maybe even slightly
later so we had Maharashtra prakrit we
had the old gurjari language which is
the mother the ancestor of the Gujarati
in Rajasthani languages and so much more
you had the various magadhi languages
every single language that exists in
India today is a descendant of the older
prakrit languages and the prakrits they
all emerged out of Sanskrit so it was
not a sister language of Sanskrit or any
such thing it was a descendant language
or Sanskrit it emerged out of the
various Corruptions that that Sanskrit
underwent languages evolve languages uh
change people you know people who live
in different parts of the world they
will eventually their languages evolve
so if you look at the Persian language
the old Persian language that was spoken
there was spoken during the accumulated
period the first millennium BC
that itself you could regard it as a
practice language because it emerged out
of Sanskrit so it was significantly
closely related to Sanskrit you could
you could actually if you read the
inscriptions that are written in the
cuneiform script but which are in the
old personal language they sound very
much like Sanskrit with certain
pronunciations changed and some words
here and there have been changed and
some grammar is kind of modified but
overall if you understand Sanskrit or
even Hindi you will understand
significant portions of what was written
uh at the time so the prakrit languages
are descendant daughter languages of
Sanskrit not sister languages there are
lots of YouTubers who these days spread
this propaganda that prakrit came before
Sanskrit Buddhism came before Hinduism
all this nonsense please don't pay
attention to this nonsense please don't
do that all right
okay uh and once again lots of questions
I saw a question but it disappeared
uh is there a chance that shinzhou's
assassination had involvement of the US
because Mr Abe wanted Japan to have an
independent foreign policy the Assassin
did not have a reasonable reason also
listen
do we have any evidence of this or that
or whatever we have no evidence
the Assassin I mean did anybody
interview the Assassin no he was taken
into custody custody by the Japanese
government and then we have no idea
what's happened with him
so he so we don't know what is what his
real motives were he was definitely an
ex-army or XX military person who who
well did this
so so we don't really know what his
motives were
he may perhaps have stated certain
motives but the real motives we don't
really know so without evidence we
cannot say who was behind this
possibilities are open many
possibilities are open
but if you
speculate and make a claim without any
evidence well you're not going to be
taken seriously so is there a chance a
chance well there are chances of lots of
things
there is a small amount of probability
that will you know if you if probability
is a hundred percent then you take out
various slices and lots of different
options are there but we don't know
which is the truth in the absence of any
actual evidence disclosed evidence so I
don't know who was behind it is there a
possibility that somebody or the other
was involved the possibility is there
but we don't have conclusion inclusive
evidence of that and therefore yeah
don't say anything
Superior to Sanskrit all right sir
all right
utkar says what's your take on Russia's
new foreign policy so the Russian
foreign policy was recently unveiled and
it's a long long document I'll not put
it on the screen because I don't have it
open anywhere but yeah also the Russian
foreign minister has come up with a
modified updated version of their
foreign policy just yesterday before
yesterday and there's a lot it's a very
lengthy document it takes it will take
you at least 10 minutes or so I would
say I if you if you want to read it
thoroughly properly
um but what's in what's interesting is
that they are focusing on two major
Nations uh focusing as in cooperation
so these two major nations are Russia
are China and India
so the Russians have said uh they say
that they they have a very privileged
and excellent relationship with India
and similar with China and they're going
to be focusing a lot on these two
Nations to cooperate from the
perspective of the mutual National
interest in mutual uh which will benefit
so uh and obviously they speak about the
U.S and the fact that the U.S seeks to
destroy and defeat Russia strategically
and on those things uh so I have not uh
studied it in great detail but these
things stood out to me straight away so
so uh
so it's clear that the Russians would
like to create a a new revised world
order that is no longer completely led
by the US the the focus is definitely on
establishing
you could say a parallel system of into
of the international order so you're
gonna have a bifurcation of the
international order on the ones one hand
you have the so-called rules-based World
Order of the United States on the other
hand we're gonna have a different system
that's going to be led by Russia India
China
and lots of other nations are interested
you have the brics
uh group of Nations five nations
including Russia India China South
Africa and uh Brazil as well other
nations are are have expressed their
desire to join it major Nations like
Saudi Arabia which is one of the major
oil producers and Mexico and lots of
other nations want to join brics
Indonesia also various African nations
so bricks looks like it's set to expand
so uh we're gonna we're gonna see lots
of changes now and Russia's foreign
policy is calibrated to make these
things happen so uh so it's clear that
there's a big change of big upheaval
that's that's currently happening in
real time in the global world order in
the Russia's in Russia's new foreign
policy is a reflection of that so they
are stating certain things explicitly
that they will cooperate with India and
China and they are also talking about
certain things have to be read between
the lines so that's my first reaction to
the Russian foreign policy maybe I
should look it look into it in great
detail perhaps make a separate video
about that but yeah that's what it is so
India is playing a kind of privileged
role in this entire matter it is
significantly
it is it is cooperating in a significant
manner with the Western Bloc with the
U.S and NATO and EU uh Nations India has
a good relationship with these nations
obviously the US has not been happy
about India's refusal to uh to play
along with their sanctions on Russia but
apart from that India has an excellent
relationship with reasonably good
relationship with the West India also is
a part of brics so it has a good
relationship with the east as well a
privileged relationship with Russia uh
not good relationship with China but
things could possibly improve possibly
depending on how Mr Xi Jinping in goes
about things his nation is also under a
lot of stress and strain right now a lot
of pressure uh things are not going as
per they had ex the way they had
expected so India is playing a very
important and interesting role India is
not
taking one side or the other in India
could end up being the bridge between
the Western Bloc and the Eastern Bloc in
India could be the nation that nobody
really uh is afraid of because India
doesn't have any expansionist hegemonic
Ambitions and it's a nation that
everybody can essentially trust so India
could could eventually in the next 20
years emerge as the global diplomatic
center of the world maybe maybe you
should we should relocate the United
Nations to India or something like that
so that's what's happening time will
tell us how it goes but that's that's
the deal and that's what I think of the
Russian foreign policy for now
uh
will I be watching WrestleMania tomorrow
no I don't watch WrestleMania anymore I
used to watch it when I was a teenager
when I was a kid uh this is a watch UFC
MMA mixed martial arts that's much more
real WrestleMania is all scripted you
know the WWE it's all scripted it's
World Wrestling Entertainment it's not
real fighting obviously the injuries are
real people do get injured the wrestlers
and all but overall it's it's scripted
it's more about entertainment the UFC
MMA is actual is about actual fighting
and you can see it I mean you can you
can tell when you see it so these days
I'm more into MMA and more into the UFC
I watch it whenever I can find the time
to watch it I prefer watching it live
but you can also watch uh re-watch uh
you know recorded
fights and all that
so yeah I will not be watching the WWE
but I do try and catch whenever I can
the UFC and Bellator as well if it's
this is it's not available in India but
we can we can look for it if it's there
rajat says how will chat GPT like
generative AI affect our lives and most
importantly our jobs how is the future
going to be like generative AI is
completely transforming the world right
now in the past people had to hire
research assistants professors would
make their students slave for them do
all the all the donkey work all the all
the boring work and then they would take
all that together and write their books
or their research papers or whatever now
we don't need that you have a virtual
assistant that you can well all you have
to do is pay 20 a month I mean uh chart
gbt 3.5 is completely free and charge
GPD 4 is I think 20 a month you also
have Google bard you also have Bing AI
well Bing and chart GPT are essentially
the same thing but they behave in
different ways there are different
flavors of the same thing you also have
things like uh stable diffusion and and
Dal e and uh there's this thing on
Discord which is all about generating
images based on various prompts so uh
that so you can create any kind of
artwork in anybody's style nowadays uh
there was a an issue with the fingers it
would make fingers look weird in the
past I think that is being addressed
right now
so soon you will have extremely
realistic images that the AI can spit
out at the moment's notice uh I'm sure
obviously that also will cost some money
but it's not a whole lot of money
it's not a whole of money a lot of money
it's not unaffordable for most people
not for students obviously students
cannot spend that kind of money but once
you once you have a job and all you can
set aside a bit of money if you if you
are so inclined so uh so it's gonna put
artists out of business but you can tell
sometimes you know these days you can
still tell what kind of art is AI
generated but as newer and better more
powerful iterations of these AIS come
out
um the art is going to be
indistinguishable from reality from from
let's say a photographic image or the
art created by an artist So eventually
you're gonna be able to create any kind
of image that you want any any image
that you want these days on Twitter you
you had all these fake AI images coming
out of Donald Trump being arrested and
and the pope wearing some weird white uh
jacket or something like that and lots
of images of Elon Musk keep coming out
so you can generate just about anything
it looks incredibly realistic and in the
next year or two it's gonna look
indistinguishable from reality
so it's gonna put photographers out of
business it's going to put artists out
of business you know it's gonna put
graphic artists and Painters out of
business for sure I don't know how those
professions will will keep up with the
advances in AI
um it's gonna it's gonna essentially
totally make the education system
irrelevant
you can now get a complete education
just from Ai and you can make the AI you
know the generative AI like Bing or chat
GPT act as a tutor and the tutoring and
education you can receive from that is
far superior to anything most professors
can offer you so you can you can gain
you know a master's degree level of
knowledge even PhD level knowledge from
this already 20 a month that's it it's
incredibly cheap why would you spend
like I don't know how much it costs one
semester in the US Indians spend a huge
amount of money to go to the us all all
that they are seeking is either good and
you know migrate to the west or come
back with a degree from a U.S University
well all of these degrees are already
becoming worthless
so it's it's transforming a lot of
things it's gonna transform the creative
sectors uh when you when you take Ai and
and
and and knew you uh combined then with
that with robotics it's gonna put a lot
of assembly line workers and all these
workers out of business so it's going to
totally transform the world in the next
six months to the next 10 years it's
going to be totally transformed the
entire world and um so it's it's lots of
professions will become redundant lots
of people will lose jobs thus far I
don't see anybody has lost their jobs
thus far but we are in the infancy of
the AI Revolution
you know and people have written books
about Ai and all that but uh you know
some of these very celebrated books have
totally failed to anticipate the rise of
the chat bots so I'm not talking about
anybody in specific I'm not I'm not
trying to create any controversy here
but that's the thing so it's going to
totally transform the world from the job
perspective in the career and profession
perspective it's also going to transform
the way geopolitics works uh there are
nations that are really investing in AI
from a military and geopolitical
perspective and those developments are
not going to be visible to anybody
that is all happening behind closed
doors so it's going to totally transform
the world in the next uh five to ten
years I right now like I said nobody has
lost their jobs thus far as we can see
nobody has come out in on social media
complaining I lost my job because of AI
it's not happened thus far it's going to
happen
it's going to happen
so programmers like I miss that uh
programmers will no longer be needed I
mean AI already spits out any kind of
code you want it can spit out python
code it can spit out coupon code for
God's sakes
it's an almost you know Legacy language
from the 1960s COBOL is still very
important because it runs the main
frames that are behind lots of you know
Legacy uh Systems Credit Card systems
and whatnot it's still a very big deal
if you are a Cobalt programmer it's it's
a very lucrative uh skill to have
uh it's a very Niche skill now ai can
spit out any kind of cobalt code that
you want uh identification Division and
whatever else division all that stuff
you know I mean I it was shocking to see
that code again after so many so many
years but yeah so AI will put
programmers out of business web
developers out of business it can create
websites you know it can create apps
apps on on iOS or Android so all you
will need now you don't even need to
know programming you just need to
have have ai hand hold you and you're
going to be able to create apps you're
going to be able to create websites
you're going to be able to do so many
things
so it's going to transform the world and
it's still a little early to predict how
it's going to go but I think it's going
to shake up the whole world and people
will have to adapt
certain things may not be replaceable
but I am sure in in two years time you
could create this what I'm doing here is
an AI I mean AI could output a fake
version of me speaking just like me and
saying the same things I would so
typically say and you would not be able
to tell the difference that also may
happen
music AI is already generating good
music a reasonably good music music that
you can use in as a background music for
various videos and things like that uh
soon it will be able to generate
excellent high quality top quality music
that's coming
video is going to come so it's gonna
totally revolutionize the world I'm not
sure what the consequences of that is
gonna be are gonna be
um
soon it will happen that you know AI you
will have your own personalized AI it
will give you exactly the kind of music
that you enjoy the various genres and
various moods that you have that you
like that sort of thing it will write
novels for you the kind of tastes that
you have based on that and so so much
more you may even see news coming in
various flavors individually tailored to
individual to various people and you
will not really know what is true and
what's not what's right and what's wrong
what's for fake news what's True News
so there's a whole amount of
possibilities out there
um and it all depends on how AI is used
like any technology AI is just a
technology uh
so any technology can be used for good
or for bad fire when it was discovered
was used for cooking which made
everyone's life easier it was also used
for Warfare
fire then steel can be used for good it
can be used for bad sticks can be good
would be used for good as well as bad
nuclear energy has good uses and bad
uses similarly AI is just another tool
in that minor it can be you it depends
on who's using it uh so typically it's
it's the military any new technology
emerges transformative technology
emerges it's typically governments in
the military that make the first use of
that and so that's also what's happening
with AI it's happening behind closed
doors we don't know what is what
developments are happening but yeah it's
going to affect all of us so AI is
something that we're going to have to
revisit and revisit in great detail
who was head over heels for John Wick 4.
I haven't seen it I think I've seen the
first first one or two movies there were
good movies Keanu Reeves it's good I
mean great guy great actor I haven't
seen four but let's see maybe good I
suppose
are a bunch of daughter languages of
Sanskrit uh they came after Sanskrit
all right uh
FFF says what would have happened if
during the turkic invasions of India
powerful and ruthless King Emperor like
Ashoka was in power with the entire
subcontinent United under him it's very
clear the turkic invasions would have
been smashed the reason the turkic
invasions succeeded eventually after two
three centuries of attempting to invade
India this it succeeded because India
was not unified politically see
political unity and disunity is a
cyclical thing cyclical thing there are
Cycles historical Cycles Imperial Cycles
so there have been times when India was
unified under a single leadership like
the mauryan Empire like the kushan
Empire like the Gupta Empire and so on
and there have been times when India was
not unified under a single Emperor or
Empire and you had lots of different
various Kings and kingdoms and all that
so the Turks caught India at the wrong
time when India was not politically
United's Empire had had gone the Gupta
Empire had gone the cholas were focusing
in south on southeast Asia a thousand
years ago in the Chola empire did not
last long after that after the demise of
rajaraja and rajendra Chola so the Turks
started their invasions and they
conducted their invasions at a time when
India was non-political United if India
was politically United under a king like
Ashoka like under an emperor like Ashoka
or
let's say kanishka or let's say uh one
of the Gupta Emperors like skanda Gupta
or or samudra Gupta there is no way the
turkic invasions would have succeeded
there would have been smashed out of
existence so the the Turks caught India
at the wrong time and that's what
happened so obviously this is all
hypothetical but we can make such
predictions based on the cycle cyclical
events of History
so even someone even the most ruthless
and barbaric invader
like Alexander the Greek he wanted to
invade India but India was unified under
the Nanda Empire at the time and the
invasion was a miserable failure it was
a miserable failure so and Alexander
most likely was defeated by this small
Frontier King small little Chieftain
called purushottam who's called purus by
the Greeks and he had to go back limping
to Babylon where he died of his injuries
and his his great horse bucephalus died
in the Battle I think the battle of the
satellite is one of these battles uh so
when India is Unified when India is
United under a single leadership a
strong leadership it's impossible
to invade and Conquer India
so that's that's what would have
happened if India was unified at the
time
okay chiragavasti says why can't we find
any evidence of Kingdoms and palaces of
all the great Kings of India like
Etc but they can find their forts did
they not have palaces at all well look
at the evidence look at the evidence I
have said this multiple times that
Indians Indian Kings did not have great
palaces luxurious palaces the the Indian
kings were
supposed to be were expected to be
Servants of the people in the nation so
that was the greatest that was the
highest morality of the king or Emperor
to serve the nation and the people not
to serve himself not to enrich himself
or herself in the case of a female
I mean if you look at somebody more
recent like the great Queen ahalia by
holkar her the house she lived in is it
still exists it was not a palace it was
a regular house she did not live in a
palace she was a very powerful Queen she
was one of the greatest Queens we've had
in the past thousand years she did so
much good for the people and for the for
the for for the civilization and for the
people she lived in a very modest house
look at the various maratha Kings the
great Chaturbate what kind of Palace did
he live in he did not live in a palace
we have to understand the difference
between a fort and the palace a fort is
a defensive fortification it has
military it has a military purpose it's
not a palace obviously you will have
quarters for a king where you can you
know have your Council and do planning
and strategy and all that and it has to
be well furnished and all that but a
fort is a military fortification it is a
military purpose a strategic and
defensive purpose a tactical purpose as
well
so when it comes to the greatest of our
Emperors rulers whether it is the
mauryan Emperors or the kushan Emperors
like like kanishka the Gupta Emperors we
know where their capitals were where do
you find the palace you do find forts we
one of kanishka so the the force that
kanishka built it still exists in
somewhere in Punjab I forget the place
and yeah
and in the example people give these
days is that you're wrong because the
rajput Kings
of the past for 600 years or so they had
palaces well that came much later after
the turkic occupation of India and
and even those those were actually forts
with a certain amount of luxury in them
yes but historically before India was
before the past Thousand Years the past
Millennium of humiliation we had purely
Indian culture in India and you will not
find a palace anywhere you will find
forts for sure but you won't find
palaces anywhere even if you go back to
the uh so-called Harappan period you
won't you don't find any Palace anywhere
you find big buildings great buildings
like what they call the public bath
which actually happens to be a Temple's
pond
and and uh the greatest buildings are
the ones that are used for Public Works
you don't find any Palace anywhere so
the truth is that India's Kings and
Emperors did not have palaces they did
not invest in they did not use public
money the nation's money for their
personal benefit and personal luxury
they would typically live in reasonably
humble uh
abodes
and the
they do not have palaces
show me a single Palace uh that a king
or a queen or an emperor lived in from
before 1080.
from before 1080 you won't find anything
of course after the so-called princely
states were set up by the British these
princely puppets would build palaces for
themselves there are various examples
but yeah so that is the answer to this
question
uh let us see what other questions do we
have
uh
Shri balram says do you know that we can
see planets on Google Maps if yes then
use it to demonstrate for certain
questions because map is our best friend
yes you can I think we can see uh
the moon I'm sure we can see Mars as
well let me try and pull that up Mars on
Google Maps let's see
yes let us do that
so it's not in as much detail as you
would otherwise have like Google Earth
but we do have it let's see this
so this here is Google Mars
yeah
so you can zoom out you can zoom in it
it's essentially a repetitive pattern
but yes that's the best map that we have
how far can we zoom in ah we can see a
reasonable amount of detail here
so there are certain reasonably famous
uh locations on Mars
where is Mount Olympus I wonder
is this mons Olympus
if I click here it doesn't say anything
yeah so so the thing is that yes we can
we can
see the map of Mars I'm sure we can see
the moon as well Google does give you
that that facility so yeah yep that is
something that most people won't know so
it's good that SRI balramji has
has brought this to our attention
okay rinigan says Manipur language is
I'm not familiar with the this
terminology uh the manipuri language
that I am aware of is the methi language
which is a Tibet of urban language it
has its own script called methi make
uh
and in the past the Bengali script was
used to write the manipuri language as
the vehicle to carry the manipuri
language but now it's been changed and
now the the original manipuri script is
used for it I think there are a couple
of versions of that script as well so
it's a work in progress
and I'm sure that there must be some
kind of relationship between the methi
language the manipuri language in
various uh so-called Naga languages
there are lots of different Naga
languages uh there must be some kind of
relationship between these languages as
well unfortunately our researchers our
historians and linguists and geneticists
have not really focused on the northeast
much so we do not have great amount of
insight into these matters it's
fascinating a lot of research needs to
be done about this but the Northeast the
Far East of India is like a gold mine
when it comes to research whether it is
sociological research or historical
research or linguistic research or
genetic research it's a gold mine it's
an untapped Goldman so much interesting
research can be done which will bring
the facts to to light you know the Far
East of India is a beautiful place very
culturally unique place a very
interesting blend of of traditions and
culture and all that so you know it
would be good if our researchers would
look into this in more detail things
swapnil Mishra says why is the
phenomenon of turbulence considered to
be one of the great Unsolved Mysteries
of physics and Mathematics well when we
when it comes to turbulence we're
talking about fluid dynamics fluid flow
so fluid for flow the equations that
that govern the flow of fluids are uh
what are they called
not the Klein government equation for
sure uh
let's Google that fluid dynamics
it's something that I've never really
looked into uh because it's not been my
field of Interest
fluid dynamics what are the equations
called
um
The navier Stokes equations yes the Navy
is talking so the navier stocks
equations are very simple when you look
at them but they are devilishly
difficult to solve
and fluid flow fluid flow flow Dynamics
the the flow of fluids and mixing of
fluids it's very fractal it's very
chaotic and there are so many parameters
and variables in that so that's what
turbulence is you know the the way
fluids flow and mix with each other and
there are vortexes and all that it's
it's almost impossible to solve an
equation cleanly with with that so
that's why it's it's one of the great
Unsolved Mysteries of physics one of the
interesting things is that when you have
a drop of you know let's say you have a
tap a faucet and you have water slowly
dripping out of it drop by drop so there
is there is something called surface
tension that keeps the the the the shape
of a water drop spherical surface
tension in case you're aware of it so so
it kind of Acts Against Gravity that's
why this drop is attached to the tap but
when sufficient amount of water comes in
the force of gravity overcomes the
surface tension and then one drop comes
down so when the drop is detaching from
the water in the in the mouth of the tap
there is in a certain instant where you
have what you could construct consider
to be a singularity over there the the
the the the the place at which the drop
pinches off so fluid dynamics is in
extremely complicated field it's almost
impossible to solve equations uh uh you
know fully to to have a
so that's why what scientists typically
do is that they they look for numerical
solutions to various equations and they
try to model these systems in
supercomputers because there are so many
parameters and all that involved that
you need an extremely powerful computer
it's typically done in super computers
and you need a lot of a lot of computing
power for that so because of that it's
it's one of the great uh
it's not exactly a mystery we understand
how it works we understand the physics
behind it we understand the equations
that govern turbulence The navier Stokes
equations
it's just that you can't solve them
solve this equation these are extremely
difficult to solve uh so so that's the
thing about fluid dynamics and
and
turbulence
okay who look at this
says who was Ivan Ivan the Terrible he
was one of the great Emperors of Russia
I don't remember which century he lived
in but he kind of Consolidated the
Russian Empire and and expanded it
greatly and he was very terrible here
this terrible temper I think he even
caused the death of his own son he
struck him with something and his son
died as a result so and and uh he was
very brutal very cruel
extremely short-tempered but he did
expand the Russian Empire significantly
and strengthened Russia so that's why
he's considered to be one of the strong
and great Emperors of Russia but a very
terrible guy so that's what I can tell
you in in brief I think there is this
this
painting
even the terrible kills his son of a
yeah there is Ivan the Terrible and his
son Yvonne so let me put that on the
screen briefly this guy didn't because
of his temper he ended up ended up
killing his own son
and this is a painting of that
even the terrible and his son Ivan so
then he realized what he done what he
has done but there was something you
could do about it after he grievously
injured his son
so yeah that is Ivan the Terrible one of
the well
one of the more remarkable historical
figures from from Russia from Russia
right let's take other questions as I
can see there are lots of questions
coming in
says how does learning about history and
geopolitics help in business and
investing look when it comes to business
let's let's talk about business first
business is about competition
it's about competing with others who are
in your field uh in your industry
so what is business it's about so it's
about identifying solutions that affect
society in solving those problems and
monetizing the solution to those
problems
and typically in any industry which is
aimed at solving certain problems you
will have various actors who are uh
who are competing with each other in
providing Solutions
so you have to
in some ways cooperate with some of them
in some cases you have to compete with
some of them so that is extremely
similar to what happens in geopolitics
we have one planet we have different
nations some Nations stick together and
cooperate when it comes to their uh
their shared interests
and in some cases you have Nations that
compete in some cases you have Nations
that go to war against each other it's
the same thing happens in business
so the principles are pretty much
similar or almost the same
investing now even in investing if you
look at the geopolitical trends and if
you look at the the investing patterns
of the various uh National Banks like
the RBI or the Federal Reserve or the or
the bank of Japan and all that and you
see what they've been doing the past 50
years or 100 years
then you can also learn a lot about
investing in in as to how they they
wrote the various Winds of Change and
how they uh adapted and changed and
molded their investing strategies as to
what to invest in Nations also invest in
things
um Every Nation the national bank will
invest in in gold for instance uh in U.S
treasury bonds nowadays nations are
dumping that so it kind of tells you how
things are going
so uh and to and to understand
geopolitics you obviously have to
understand history well so
you you know
there is this this book of strategy it's
a book of stratagems called The Art of
War it's written by a person called Sun
Tzu who lived in China about 2000
something years ago
and that book is used in business as a
book that uh you can
in business you know even in sport
so this the the strategies and
strategyms and tactics that you use in
Warfare in geopolitics can equally well
be applied in business and in sport and
even in investing
so yes if you can significantly broaden
your horizons study history and
geopolitics in detail you will certainly
be able to take the same lessons that
you've learned from here geopolitics and
apply them in business and investing and
other spheres of life so very
interesting question that's something
that uh most people don't quite see very
good to see this question
Etc was recently talking to one and he
was confident about his non-indian
Heritage my question is why do you have
to convince anybody
why what are you going to gain out of it
what will India gain out of it let them
believe whatever they want to believe
it's their choice uh
I I personally never try to convince
anyone of anything if somebody has a set
of beliefs I say good luck enjoy
we know what the facts are then why do
we have to convince others how will it
see people have beliefs that they have
internalized that they hold on to those
beliefs very strongly
most people don't want to change their
mind most people don't think logically
rationally and it's it's a Fool's errand
trying to convince somebody who has no
interest in changing their mind no
matter how much evidence you throw at
them so my policy is very simple I don't
waste my time trying to convince anybody
people ask me questions I answer the
questions it's up to them to believe me
or not it's entirely their choice
I'm not gonna waste my time convincing
somebody so I would say that why are you
supposed to convince a Pakistani about
the truth why
what are you getting out of it what will
India gain from it
so uh So my answer is why should you do
it
uh and and I don't really know about any
strategy or tactics as to how to
convince somebody who doesn't want to
listen to the truth so I think it's a
it's actually a waste of time please
ramay don't waste your time doing all
this uh
I'm sure you have a lot of energy and in
a bit of time so use it wisely and
judiciously and don't waste it on people
who have no interest in in seeing the
truth that's what I would say
all right uh
wait I thought either was Ragnar's son
we were talking about Ivan the Terrible
not Ivar
I were the Boneless these are two
different individuals from two different
time periods
the spelling of Ivan the Terrible is i v
a n
the spelling of Iowa the Boneless is i v
a r there's a difference between R and M
why am I even doing this oh God
please
all right what's the future of gaming
gaming is a huge industry I think gaming
is a bigger industry today than the
entertainment industry I think gaming
the gaming industry overall is bigger
than Hollywood and all of this put
together
so uh these days you know with the the
Advent of all these devices portable
devices mobile phones and tablets and
iPads and Android tablets in laptops or
which is like a thing of the past kind
of all these things because of this now
everybody has a device even
three-year-old kids have their own
device nowadays so everybody is
engrossed in there and everybody keeps
on doing playing some games which gives
you this dopamine release and makes you
feel pleasure so it's something that's
extremely addictive
and yeah so it's something that's going
to continue
so I think gaming is going to be a very
big industry it's kind of catching on in
India as well you have gaming uh
Esports Esports is also gaming isn't it
uh so Esports is taking off in India
lots of uh Gamers prominent gamers are
becoming influencers they're making a
lot of money out of that so I think
gaming is Gonna Keep on growing
It's Gonna Keep on growing and I don't
know if there are any gaming uh
uh developers or or companies in India
itself
but yeah so what Indians consume is is
Western games
earlier we had pubg which is a Chinese
thing but it's been banned in India for
for obvious reasons so I think the
future of gaming is bright as an
industry it's gonna make a lot of money
and with the Advent of AI you're going
to have ai enabled games and much better
graphics and and so I I suppose with the
Advent of AI just about anybody could
start developing games you will not need
a huge team of people to work under you
you know a bunch of people who work on
the graphics and bunch of people who
work at the storyline and a bunch of
people who do the programming the coding
and putting all that together you need a
big game for that you know it's a lot of
money but with the I don't have ai I
think even individuals could start
creating games good games or high
quality games and you have platforms
like steam I believe and Xbox and
Playstation Etc which are some of the
major platforms that I can I can think
of I'm sure there are more as well so I
think gaming the gaming industry is an
industry that is going to keep on
growing and I think it's poised for for
uh definitely becoming much bigger it's
already bigger than the entertainment
industry I think it could eventually end
up dwarfing the entertainment industry
to the end users the consumers I would
say that use it judiciously it's fun to
play a game even I've done that I had a
I had one of the earlier you know today
what's what's the version of PlayStation
that we have is it PS4 or PS5
we have one of those two I had a PS2
the PS1 was this enormous box the PS2
was a sleeker box so I I had bought a
PS2 I think in 2004 or something and I
had a few games that I used to play one
of them a car racing game I was more
about more like a car crashing game or
something so I I used to play once in a
while the thing is if you spend your
whole day doing this you will end up
doing nothing in life so yeah that's
what that's a word of caution I would
like to give you I myself have
done some gaming a long time ago I no
longer do it uh because I have too much
else to do you know so uh it's it's it's
a good Outlet to you know so let off
some steam have some fun but don't do it
too much maybe an hour or two maximum
per day is I think already too much yeah
I think in China they have they have
restricted kids their online time to
about two hours per week that's what Mr
SRI Jinping has done I think that's a
little bit excessive but I can
understand the the thought process
behind it
uh
so yeah that's what I think about the
future of gaming interesting question
that you have asked
all right let's see Arya saying what are
the findings of the excavation of the
submerged dwarka City what are the
research papers I should read regarding
it I have no idea I don't think any
research has been done in the past 20
years so they I think it was a it was uh
the archaeologist Sr Rao who discovered
this more the submerged City more than
20 years ago maybe around 30 years ago I
think it was in the 1980s or 1990s
somewhere around that time definitely
before the 21st century and after this
discovery they've done nothing about it
nothing
the ASI is doing nothing as far as I
know if I am mistaken I'm I will be
happy to to admit the mistake but as far
as I know they have been doing nothing
what should be happening is underwater
archeology
and that site should be well preserved
and we should ensure that no dredging
happens or no such no no other activity
happens there I don't even know what's
happening there
and uh they they also have discovered
the entire Gulf of khambab Gulf of cambe
archaeological complex which is not just
one
it's a whole network
of underwater cities so it's like like
10 12 000 years old you know
um so I don't think any any significant
archaeological work is happening
when it comes to dwarka or the Gulf of
combat archaeological complex I have no
idea what research papers exist uh it's
it's I mean I've looked for it I I can
find almost nothing so I don't know
I'm I'm I have found various articles in
various websites in blogs and all that
but that's not quite a research paper
and it doesn't have the the the
credibility of a research paper so I
hope the ASI looks into this matter I
mean it's up to the government to to to
direct them to do certain things
the ASI see there are some good people
in the ASI uh Sr
was one of the great archaeologists Dr
Bibi Lal I who
Dr bibilal was once the head of the ASI
he's one of the greatest archaeologists
the world has ever seen
so the ASI has produced some good
archaeologists some some great ones but
the majority of the archaeologists I
believe are they they have this
bureaucratic mindset and the leadership
of the ASI I mean whoever runs it is
typically bureaucrats so I don't know
what mindset they have what agenda they
have what Outlook they have but clearly
they they they're they're not doing what
needs to be done
so that is disappointing I have said
this in the past that the ASI actually
ideally should be disbanded completely
and a new Professional Organization
needs to be created from scratch
to and the funding should be invested
into that so yeah so I don't really know
what's happening with work I don't think
anything is being done in recent times
in the past 10 years at least
says please tell us about ding shopping
and his contribution to China's growth
so then shopping came to power after the
after uh you could say in the aftermath
of the deaths of the great Chairman Mao
and then shopping
he took
the nation of China in a totally
different direction under Mao there's a
lot of mismanagement there were there
was the cultural revolution the Great
Leap Forward which your enormous
disasters when it came to China
I don't know close to a I don't know
some the that's the death stall is
between 40 and 80 million Chinese people
and it it these economies suffered
greatly as a result there were famines
and all kinds of disasters so doing
shopping wanted a more modern approach
he wanted China to become rich and
prosperous he said I believe that that
being rich is glorious and we should be
rich
so he set about transforming China's
economy in the the way the entire nation
was run he took his inspiration from the
great uh
the great Singaporean dictator
benevolent dictator Lee Kuan Yew uh and
he said that you know Lee Kuan Yew was
was then shopping said that Lee Kuan Yew
was fortunate that he had to only turn
around the fortunes of a city-state
Singapore
so it can be done in Shanghai or
whatever but if you have a nation the
size of China it will take a lot of
energy a lot of effort and a lot of time
to achieve something similar to what
then shop to what Lee Kuan Yew was able
to do in just 20 years
so he uh so after the the Advent of then
shopping the Chinese sent lots of
officials to Singapore to study the
Singaporean methods how they had gone
about doing things and then they set
about replicating the same in China
uh so drink shopping is the guy who
started the transformation of China into
from from a third world extremely poor
starving nation into a nation that is
now the world's second largest economy
it is Deng Xiaoping who started the
process and to a large extent it is then
shopping who's responsible for a
significant amount of China's success
and he uh said that China needs to hide
and bite hide your capabilities and bide
your time which means don't most don't
publicize your greatness if you have any
uh hide your capabilities work as hard
as possible and wait for the right time
so he passed away a long time ago but uh
it was Mr Xi Jinping who I think in 2012
decided that the right time is now and
that's what started the wolf Warrior
diplomacy in China's belligerent uh
Newfound belligerence which we can now
see it's been there for a decade at
least uh so that's about ding shopping
the guy who totally transformed China he
he started the process that transformed
China
and it was during his time that China
started militarizing as well uh
the naval build up that we that China
now has the world's largest navy by
numbers uh not necessarily the most
powerful navy but definitely the largest
Navy in terms of numerical strength so
all of these things that we that China
currently enjoys
the root of all that is doing shopping
so definitely the greatest leader China
produced uh in the past after them after
them
obviously did a lot of mismanagement but
obviously he also
is one of the greats
from the Chinese perspective so
so yeah that's thing shopping
all right let's uh
let's see other questions
uh just another nerd how do
gravitational waves look like in three
dimensions
and when will you open a Discord server
that's totally two two very different
servers how do gravitational waves look
look like in three dimensions
yeah go to a lake or a pond right
take a stone and drop it throw it into
the bond what do you see you're gonna
see a splash and you're gonna see
ripples radiate outwards that's what
gravitational waves look like in three
dimensions
so you have length your bread then you
have height
that's exactly like what gravitational
is look like in three dimensions
obviously space time is four dimensional
so you can't really visualize that
because there's the element of time as
well and gravitational waves also affect
time it's going to cause ripples not
just in space but also in time so the
actual gravitational waves are four
dimensional waves but to think of it in
three dimensions you have to think of
exactly like what happens when you throw
a stone a pebble onto the surface of a
lake or a pond and you see ripples
radiating outwards in concentric circles
that's what gravitational waves look
like so when you have a gravitational
event like like let's say the merger of
two black holes the merger of two
neutron stars or neutron star in black
hole you're gonna see gravitational
waves radiating outwards in the same
manner and the amplitudes means which
means the height of the waves is going
to be very high when it comes to the
merger of two black holes because it's a
very very powerful and energetic event
so in that case in the merger of two
black holes you're gonna see a
gravitational not a wave but actually a
tsunami enormous and that's why we are
able to detect it all the way over here
because it's only the largest waves that
the the large that Lego can detect so
that's what a gravitational waves look
like in three dimensions when will I
open a Discord server I'm in the process
of opening a Discord server it's going
to be managed properly and
professionally this time last time I had
not hired anybody to do it it was being
it was kind of you know not not going
well and I obviously don't have a huge
amount of time to come every day and
interact with people so I need somebody
to manage it professionally so it's it's
in the process of being set up it
actually exists if you if you know where
to look right that's about the Discord
server
um
all right let's see some of the
questions
who are Caucasian hunter-gatherers CSG
are there some way are they in some way
related to India
see what is the Caucasus
let's find the cocasses shall we for
that we have to go to the map the map is
our best friend
so when we talk about the core casters
we're talking about the the Union
which connects which is the piece the
land mass between the Black Sea and the
Caspian Sea that region is called the
Caucasus right it's it's called kafka's
in Russian so uh we have Southern Russia
we have chechnya we have Dagestan
Georgia Armenia and Azerbaijan that is
the Caucasus
so in the distant past you had a bunch
of hunter-gatherers who lived there
those are the Caucasian hunter-gatherers
are they in some way related to India I
think see eventually everybody is
related to each other because as we know
the the best evidence that we have
as of today tells us
that Humanity originated in Africa and
humans crossed over
from Africa into Eurasia most likely
over here the Baba al-mandib Strait this
was the closest point so they somehow
crossed over our ancestors from here
into the Arabian peninsula and the
coastline of the Arabian Peninsula had
some greeneries that's why they were
able to travel and migrate and once
again they had to cross the Persian Gulf
from across the Strait of Hormuz and
they came into
Asia
and the coastal regions again over here
where kind of they had some vegetation
so they went eastwards and eventually
they came into India and India was
completely lush green so that's where
Humanity first settled down after the
Out of Africa migration that is some 75
000 or so years ago and it was so India
was the first Founders zone of the Out
of Africa migration and from India
Humanity migrated in all directions
east west north and south eventually
humans ended up in Australia at some 60
or 65 000 years ago and uh so it was
from India that humans migrated East as
well as West and eventually into Europe
where they encountered neanderthals
there were some intermixing of the
genetics
and so on so the Caucasian
hunter-gatherers were the descendants of
all of these two intro back and forth
migrations but where the Caucasian
hunter-gatherers in somewhere related to
India so in that way with the related
obviously we need more genetic evidence
to see if there is any
closer genetic Affinity between the CH G
individuals and ancient Indians who
lived in India at that time
so that's what I can tell you
what else do we have
lots of questions as always
this is by Anisha recently bhutan's King
was given respect in Germany just after
that for the first time a democratic
elections took place in Bhutan followed
by comments on doklam by Bhutan this is
the U.S behind it see I understand
the US is the most powerful nation in
the world they
have an enormous amount of influence
everywhere in the world including inside
India
so uh so I have not followed this chain
of events that bhutan's King was given
respect in Germany see typically when a
head of state king queen Prime Minister
President Etc goes to another country
they are given respect
anywhere you go even you go to even if
you go to a nation that's kind of your
enemy you are given the kind of respect
that is given to a head of state
so I am not aware of what happened in
Germany but okay let's say this all this
is what happened
so Germany as we know is a nation that
is uh controlled by the U.S it's under
U.S military occupation since 1945.
um and I have obviously heard of the
comment on doklam by one of the
bhutanese officials about the fact that
about and he claims that it's a matter
that's that's between Bhutan China and
India that sort of thing uh so either
it's China that's behind it or it's the
U.S that's behind or maybe both are
behind it
um so we don't know right we don't know
because we don't have the information of
what happened
of what interactions and talks happened
between let's say the bhutanese
officials and the Chinese maybe or maybe
the Americans or maybe some
intermediaries somewhere else we don't
know what transpired we don't know what
happened and because we don't have this
information this evidence that's why we
can't really tell what happened and
who's behind it but there's a
possibility
that the Chinese may be behind it and
they have gained influence in Bhutan
maybe there's a possibility that maybe
the Americans are behind it and they are
trying to destabilize India's
relationship with with Bhutan or maybe
the the bhutanese themselves have made a
certain Choice possibly perhaps we don't
know yet but a Time Will Tell Us
so how will time tell us we have to keep
on observing the various statements that
the bhutanese officials and the
government make and based on the pattern
that we observe over a certain period of
time we can make a more precise
uh we can we can arrive at a more
precise and and stronger understanding
of what actually is going on and who's
behind it and what the motivations and
agendas are but yes this is something
that's that's uh currently happening and
this is something that we are all going
to keep an eye on on Bhutan and and what
stance it takes
all right uh what else
should Sanskrit and Proto dravidian be
made the two official languages of
Bharat both of them being the mother
languages of their language families
will that solve the language divide the
so-called dravidian languages are if
there is no such thing as a dravidian
language
okay this term dravidian you will not
find anywhere in India's historical
texts it is something that was created
by the British
to divide India
okay so there is also thing is
proto-dravidian which language is
proto-drividian
this isn't completely fake false
artificial category that was created by
the British
by Robert Caldwell the Christian
Missionary Robert Caldwell
he created this phrase this this phrase
this fake
categorization of Aryan versus dravidian
these are all fake categories I don't
know why we are also brainwashed and we
believe this the only what was the
language that the cholas took to
Southeast Asia
it was not Tamil it was Sanskrit
you do find some Tamil inscriptions in
there but the cholas
their their state their language they
promoted in Southeast Asia Sanskrit not
Tamil
when it comes to uh the indianization of
Southeast Asia which happened long
before the Jewelers it happened around
3000 years ago that was done by the
merchants from Kalinga present the
Orissa
what language do you find in Southeast
Asia Indian language it's it's Sanskrit
all the way to the Philippines you have
Sanskrit
the only language this divide that we
are talking about the language divide is
an artificial language device that has
been created by the British
it is being perpetuated and strengthened
by certain political factions certain
politicians for personal gain divide and
Rule that's still continuing in in India
so there is no such thing as a
prototravidian language which is the
mother language of some hypothetical
dravidian language family
India's Linguistics needs to be looked
at a priori fresh
not by existing linguists who all are
brainwashed you need a completely fresh
look at India's linguistics
if
the so-called dravidian language is very
separate language family why are the
so-called indo-aryan languages so much
closer and similar to kannada and Tulu
and Telugu Etc and Malayalam
then to German
but but apparently Hindi is part of the
Indo-European language family and yet
Hindi is so much closer Sanskrit is so
much closer to Tulu to Telugu to kannada
to Malayalam to Tamil
Etc
so clearly these these These
categorizations are completely incorrect
we have to look at India's Linguistics
from a complete a priori perspective
start from scratch again
that's what needs to happen the only
language that can be the official
language the civilization language of
India is sanskrit no other language
no other language
all right what do we have what else do
we have
hahaha
kid says should young people enter
politics if yes how can one start by
joining a political party or creating a
new one let's say you want to create a
new political party how will you create
it
how will you
attract people to join your party
what kind of political part what kind of
leadership structure would it have let's
say you start a new political party why
should people accept you as leader you
have to ask yourself these questions and
what really goes behind into organizing
a political party and conducting
activities let's say you
form a political party you convince
let's say 100 people to join the party
and you convince them to accept you as
their leader how will you run the
activities of the political party you
need an office you need a building
you're going to need money for that if
you want to hold a rally it takes a lot
of organization coordination it takes
money
you want to hold rallies you want to
um hold and run an election campaign do
you have any idea how much money goes
into running an election campaign
huge huge huge amounts of money
politics is all about money there's a
reason why politics is all about all
about money
so if a young person wants to enter
politics
you can create a new political party but
it's not going to get an attraction
you will have to join an existing
political party that's the only actual
option that exists
you're gonna have to join a political
party
so it's good for young people to to
enter politics it's definitely good
um
and you have to understand how politics
really works you have to understand what
is the nature of power politics is all
about power there's a huge amount of
money that goes into uh running a
political movement and a party so these
are things that you have to look into
so it's good for young people to enter
politics but you it will take you some
time to get used to it and the young
people you know
there's a lot of energy there's a lot of
passion Etc you believe in certain
causes but when you're young you are
naive that is that is
you know that's something which is just
it's a fact of life if I think of myself
when I was doing how I was when I was 20
years old 20 years old I was incredibly
naive I was clueless about how the world
worked it takes time that's why they say
that in politics if a person is 45 or 50
years old that person is Young that's
what they say
so young people should certainly enter
politics but you're gonna have a long
period of time in which you're going to
be learning it's going to be a big
period of learning at least a decade in
which you will learn things and only
then will you have some maturity as to
how to navigate the world of politics
but yeah it's good for young people to
enter politics for sure
all right
pratik Jain says we are providing grains
to Taliban aren't we supporting the
Taliban to disturb and to create
problems in Pakistan is it white funding
by Indian government or Master stroke of
Modi government to weaken our enemy
listen
we are India has been supporting
Afghanistan and providing monetary
financial and humanitarian assistance
and doing development activities in
Afghanistan for at least 30 years
okay and during this time period you had
various governments that were in power
when the Taliban wasn't in power for
much of this time
so whatever
Aid and support
India is providing to Afghanistan is
meant for the people of Afghanistan
irrespective of who is in power
now there is it's not it's not a secret
that the Taliban is closely not closely
but to a certain extent aligned with
India
uh see when the Taliban took over
Afghanistan which year did it happen a
couple of years ago they took out the
Americans left Afghanistan overnight the
Taliban took over
it was a period of extreme chaos we saw
what happened the Americans are
evacuating evacuating and people are
trying to jump on those planes and it
was a disaster
the Americans left overnight it was
complete chaos and the Taliban moved in
to fill in the power vacuum and there
was a big period of chaos and
uncertainty it took the Taliban some
time to take control of the nation
so when all this was happening the
Americans were leaving and various
embassies were evacuating India was also
evacuating its Embassy in Kabul in other
places in the Taliban provided full
support to India full cooperation not a
single Indian was harassed or harmed or
delayed
in any way whatsoever nothing happened
yeah we know some journalists was was
was shot by the Taliban that's a
different story that journalist was not
part of the Indian government
um that's a whole different thing but no
Indian person apart from that one
journalist was touched by the Taliban or
harmed or hampered or abducted or
delayed or any such thing the Taliban
gave full cooperation to India
uh so India was able to evacuate all its
personnel and also some Afghans as well
out of uh Kabul and then after the
stability came back India has reopened
its Consulate in various things India is
engaging with the Taliban on the
Diplomatic front India is restarting its
humanitarian Aid to Afghanistan the
Taliban has been asking India to to
restart development activities do you
know why it's because it India's
development activities have helped the
common man woman and child in
Afghanistan India spent about well in
excess of a billion dollars in all these
activities India constructed dams India
constructed highways and Roads India
constructed the Afghan Parliament
building and much schools hospitals all
these things
India invested a lot of money in
agricultural Works in Afghanistan all of
these things they have benefited the
common man woman and child none of the
money India invested in Afghanistan has
gone in into the pockets of various
corrupt Afghan politicians
so because of this the Taliban Oso
Taliban even though it is whatever it is
it sincerely appreciates India in what
India has done
so whatever we are doing
is in support of the Afghan people it is
not in support of the Taliban if you
send let's say a thousand tons of wheat
it's gonna who is who's gonna help it's
gonna help the people of marathon it's
not gold we are sending or US Dollars
we're sending or rupees we're sending we
are sending wheat
the Taliban can't eat all the wheat
right they're gonna have to distribute
it to the people
uh
so we are supporting Afghanistan from
from a genuine desire to stabilize the
country and what India seeks is a is is
a stable
and uh peaceful Afghanistan and we India
sincerely wants the situation the the
conditions to get better for the people
of Afghanistan India obviously
I don't think India has officially
recognized the Taliban government but
India is definitely working with them
and in hand in hand in some ways
now we know
are you asking about Pakistan here uh
see when the Taliban took over people
were saying lots of famous geopolitical
commendative theaters were saying that
this is a disaster for India the Taliban
are a Pakistani creation at that time I
had said
at that time I had said that Taliban is
going to be Pakistan's number one enemy
the Taliban are pashtoon nationalists
and they do not recognize the Pakistan
Afghanistan border which was the Duran
line created by the British there are
significant Pursuit majority areas that
are currently within Pakistan the
pashtunistan region the Northwestern
Frontier Province I said the Taliban
wants it back they wanted to be part of
Afghanistan again so there is a big
massive border dispute between Pakistan
and Afghanistan
it doesn't matter who created the
Taliban 30 years ago today is Taliban is
an Afghan nationalist Pashto nationalist
government and they seek this territory
back
and there are various factions of the
tally but also there is the Afghan
Valley bond which rules Afghanistan now
there's the Pakistani Taliban which the
pakistanis considered to be a terrorist
organization which is not exactly run by
the by the Afghans it also will have
pashtuns but it is based out of Pakistan
and it seeks to uh wage war against the
Pakistani government in the Pakistani
army
so uh whatever terrorist activities are
happening within Pakistan I mean
obviously the pakistanis themselves have
created the terrorism and the terrorists
it's coming back to bite them in the in
the back
so India is not funding any terrorist
activities India is simply helping the
people of Afghanistan
all right so India has never supported
terrorism India will never support
terrorism terrorism is is barbaric it is
inhuman and it is totally illegal
terrorism has to be Stamped Out wiped
out which is why Pakistan needs to be
dealt with eventually
so um India is not helping the Taliban
India is helping Afghanistan the Taliban
know this India is helping their people
which is why the Taliban are
significantly favorably inclined towards
India the Taliban also know that India
does not wish to conquer Afghanistan or
take any Afghan territory even in the
future when India and Afghanistan will
again have a common border India is not
going to pose any threat to Afghanistan
they know it and that's why they are so
much more favorable favorably in trying
towards India than to Pakistan despite
their religious issues and all that so
obviously the Taliban are an Islamic
Emirate they are an Islamic
fundamentalist organization which
obviously will from that perspective it
would make sense for them to be
favoritely favorable towards Pakistan
and yet it's not the case
it's because of India's track record of
helping the Afghanistan the people of
Afghanistan so India is not going to
fund any terrorist activities anywhere
whatsoever that will never happen but
yes I I expect that India will support
the Taliban government
in its uh
in its struggle against Pakistani
terrorism that certainly will happen and
that
takes various shapes and forms
okay
let's see what else
is why are Indians so inferior who says
Indians are inferior let's continue I
have seen many videshi foreign YouTubers
making reaction videos on YouTube about
India those videos get millions of views
and they make lots of money
average Europeans are not like that
that's very interesting yeah
you have all kinds of reaction videos on
YouTube so reaction to some Indian movie
like RR is a big deal these days so lots
of foreigners are reacting to RR
and these videos get millions of views
from India
and uh you also have various Pakistani
reaction channels that react to Indian
things that happen in India they react
to YouTube videos coming out of India
and all and Indians watch this and you
just enjoy watching this and obviously
you have
European and American YouTubers who make
reaction videos about India and those
also get millions of views so why is it
so it's because Indians to some EXT see
Indians are not inferior but lots of
Indians have an inferiority complex
understand the difference
the difference being between being
actually inferior and believing that you
are inferior you are not actually
inferior but you believe that you are
inferior or that some others are
superior that's called an inferiority
complex you may not be inferior to
anyone but you have been conditioned to
believe that others are better than you
that's an inferiority complex and most
Indians unfortunately
not most hopefully but many Indians have
this
so they crave
foreign validation
if
a movie comes out in India
and people from outside India start
praising it then Indians will go and
watch it and they'll say this is a great
movie but if a movie comes out which can
be great but it doesn't get any foreign
validation then Indians will not regard
that movie as very good this is an
inferiority complex that lots of Indians
have unfortunately and why is it so
where what is the root or the root cause
or the origin of this inferiority
complex it is the education system and
the media
the education system makes Indians
believe that they are you know there's
nothing great about India
and the education system portrays
foreign occupiers and destroyers of
India as being good and better than
Indians like the turko mughals Mongol
the the Turks they did a lot of good
things for India Akbar was great
apparently and the British totally
reformed Indian society and got rid of
all the evil backward aspects of Indian
society and they enlightened and
liberated us and they gave us this great
English language and they gave us
Western education
and they taught Indians Math and Science
because India never had these things
and they built Railways for us and they
gave us the British law the Judiciary
without the British we would have never
had anything so all of this is brainwash
brainwashing and this is what you're
taught in the education system
and we are told
most Indians grow up believing that the
British liberated India from the from
the mughals from the Turks which is not
the case the British actually defeated
the maratha Empire which had already
liberated India from the mughals so the
education system brainwashes Indians
into feeling that they are totally
inferior to everybody else
and the media and Bollywood
continue that
so you were taught a certain
kind of thing as when you're growing up
and what you learn when you're growing
up you cherish that you cherish those
memories and you hold on to that for
dear life and then after you are a
teenager and after you grown up you
watch Bollywood you watch the news media
and all that and all of this keeps on
reinforcing all these Notions that you
have and that's why Indians have this
inferiority complex in which they
believe that Outsiders are better
they're Superior
so if they say something nice about
India we should really Rejoice so when
an Indian movie gets some kind of a
college or a word from outside it's like
a great celebration in India who cares I
mean I don't care but most Indians do so
that's the reason why it is like this
and that's why Indians uh that's why
these foreign YouTubers who make
reaction videos or whatever about India
they get so many views and it's it's a
great it's a great business for them
yeah that's how it is
okay
um
saurabh says I wasted my 12th standard
2022 in a drop here I want to become an
engineer or scientist can I still become
I'm addicted to the mobile phone what
can I do please guide me listen if you
are addicted addicted to something you
want to break the addiction the best way
of doing it I would imagine is to
replace that activity with something
else which is equally interesting or
uh or worthwhile
uh so listen if you wasted one year
that's okay you can always go back the
next year do your 12th and continue on
the path it's not going to affect you
too much in the long run
uh if you are addicted to the mobile
phone to some extent it's about
willpower put it down
and open the book and study
right uh
so I I don't know I'm not an addiction
counselor or something and I really
haven't really faced any major addiction
or anything so I don't know how one
would go about overcoming an addiction I
think the I would imagine the best way
to give up an addiction is to
you know draw into your reserves of
willpower put down the mobile phone or
maybe give yourself you know
come to an agreement with yourself that
I will use the mobile phone doing all
the scrolling and whatever you do one
hour a day maximum that will be my
reward for doing all the study that I'm
supposed to do something like that so
you have to become disciplined at the
end of the day it's your responsibility
nobody else is going to help you out you
have to find the strength and the
willpower and the willingness to do what
is what is best for you
so the motivating factor is that should
be that you want to become an engineer
or scientist that should motivate you
and if the motivation is strong enough
then you'll be able to do it so uh it's
okay if you dropped one year so what big
deal life is long you're gonna live to
100 okay so one year is not going to
make a big difference go back the next
year study hard get you get your 127
done and then move on in life
that is what I would tell you
from the big picture perspective
pratik says why do Latin Americans have
this same skin tone and facial structure
like South Asians I strongly dislike
this term South Asians what is South
Asia
it's the Indian subcontinent
right so uh so let me go to the map
and let's let's make the map flat for a
change
is the flat map so look at the latitudes
look at the latitude where India is at
if you click here it says what 34.84
and 77 point something
so India lies between
the 36th latitude
and let's say
the equator
so between those latitudes we also have
Mexico
so it makes sense that the people who
live in the same latitudes will have a
similar kind of skin tone
because we get similar amounts of
sunlight
so uh and obviously in in the southern
hemisphere also you have the same
latitudes up to 30 or something 36 let's
say ah let us go further around here so
that's why
the people who live up to up to let's
say Uruguay Argentina
and up to the northern part of Mexico
and all that historically the people who
live there would have a very similar
skin color as the people who live in the
Indian subcontinent
so it's the amount of sunlight that you
receive that typically determines your
skin tone and skin color uh facial
features and all uh that that is I I
don't know we don't quite have the
answer maybe we would need to look into
the genetics but skin color I can
definitely answer it's because of the
same attitudes in the same amount of
sunlight that you receive so even people
in Northern Africa
they would have similar skin tones as
the people of India and and so on
the facial structure the facial features
yeah it's true you know lots of Indians
when they go to the US they are kind of
mistaken for what they call Hispanic
people because you you have a similar a
very similar skin color and similar
facial features as well
so when it comes to facial features I'm
not quite sure why it is so maybe the
answer lies in this the feel of genetics
perhaps
so that's some some something that has
not quite been
researched thus far
Ian says can there be dimensions in
fractions like 1.5 or 2.5 Dimensions
what are your thoughts on can there be a
third dimension of mathematics
is first and second a real number line
and complex numbers
see the real number line is not a
dimension the complex
number line is not a dimension that's
that's not how how you look at you you
have the complex field and all so you
have to go deeper into mathematics to
understand that these are not Dimensions
these are different ways of looking at
numbers
now can there be Factor Dimensions
fractional Dimensions so uh you have
Euler's number let me put that on the
screen eulers
number it's called e right I think in
school and all we all learn about the
number Euler's number which is
2.718 whatever yeah 2.7182818
Etc it's it's a
uh
it's an irrational number it can be
represented as this uh summation
you know so uh recently Dr subashkak Who
has been on my podcast at least twice if
I recall correctly at least twice so he
has come up with this new Theory
in which the e-universe may not be
three-dimensional or four dimensional or
10 or 11 or 26 dimensional it may
actually be e dimensional e dimensional
so the universe may not have
all these dimensions three or four or
whatever it may have 2.7183 Dimensions
which which makes no sense because you
know we cannot visualize dimensions in
that manner but maybe our senses kind of
don't tell us what really happens what's
really out there it would be too
complicated for our brain or our minds
to process cognitively in real time so
maybe what we see of the world is in our
simplification of what is really out
there because see
look at the color spectrum okay
color spectrum
you know the colors right the color of
the rainbow vibgy or
now weak perceive colors this is the
color spectrum do you see pink in here
the color pink doesn't exist in the
Spectrum
do you see the color black in here the
black color doesn't exist in the
Spectrum
the gray color gray it also is not part
of the spectrum so black and pink and
gray are non-spectral colors they don't
even exist and yet we see these colors
which tells you that the brain the mind
the Consciousness is somehow
interpreting certain combinations of
color of of the electromagnetic spectrum
light and the absence of electromagnetic
light in some in some frequencies as the
color pink magenta or black or gray so
these are non-spectral colors so this
should give you an indication of the
fact that what we see is not really what
the universe is
sometimes it is an oversimplification
so similarly maybe we have
2.7183 Dimensions instead of three
but we see it as three just to simplify
things because if we see it in the the
universe with the in the true complexity
that it has then our little brains will
not be able to process all this
information cognitively in real time and
if we can't process the information
properly it will hamper our chances of
surviving long term
so that's the thing so it is certainly
possible that the universe may actually
have
2.7183 dimensions
interesting
okay let us see
other questions
Rahul says how would a hypothetical war
between Rome and the mauryas have played
out in the first century CE
okay a hypothetical question let's look
at the map as always
so to understand I have a hypothetical
war between the Romans and the mauryas
we have to first understand how far Rome
Italy is from
the modern Empire which is India let's
do a straight line distance
over here that's 6 000 kilometers
roughly uh if you were to uh
okay let's clear this
let's say we go to the uh Eastern Fringe
of the Roman Empire let's say we we go
to let's say Thrace which is current day
uh where Eastern Europe
and we measure this distance from there
to to the border of the modern Empire
which is Afghanistan let's see
that is still 3000 kilometers so any
such War would happen at enormous
distances the Romans would have either
to come all the way to India or the
mauryan Empire would have had to go all
the way into the Roman Empire
so whoever has to travel large distances
is going to be at a disadvantage because
you have to essentially live off the
land you have to either live of the land
or carry enormous amounts of resources
very long distances which gives you a
significant disadvantage or maybe let's
say that the war was fought in the
Caucasus region
so then the question arises which empire
has more had more resources so if you I
don't have the GDP figures over here
right now but India at that time
accounted for at least a third of the
entire globe's GDP and Europe was a
fraction
of that a fraction which means the Roman
Empire was a fraction of that so
obviously the mauryan Army the modern
Empire would have would have had access
to way more resources than the Romans
so your military strength is going to be
proportional to your GDP
and the Indian GDP modern GDP was way
way way greater than the Roman GDP which
means that the mauryan Empire the Army
would have had a significant advantage
over the Romans yes we are we are shown
Rome you know in in popular media in in
writing in various TV series and movies
we are Rome is portrayed as this
enormous massive all-conquering Empire
the truth is that it was nothing
comparable to the modern Empire it was
not
the modern Empire never sought to expand
out of the Indian subcontinent
so it was a choice that the modern
Emperors made if they had chosen to
expand and Conquer other territories
they would have been able to do it
reasonably easily
the kushan empire did conquer
significant parts of of Eurasia the
kushan Empire's uh
borders lay at the shores of the Caspian
Sea and the aralsi it also the koshan
Empire also included much of present-day
xinjiang which is currently occupied by
China
there was an enormous Empire it was all
done through Conquest military conquest
mainly by kanishka the great
so Indian empire certainly were capable
of expanding if they so desired and if a
hypothetical war between Rome and the
mauryan Empire let's say had happened
the modern Empire would most likely have
prevailed and defeated the Roman Empire
that's an interesting question you asked
here Rahul
okay
let us see some other questions or
samarth says why were turkey and Hungary
not invited to Biden's democracy Summit
but Pakistan was invited Pakistan
rejected the invitation
see uh I'm not quite sure what this
democracy Summit is all about the US is
not really a democracy I mean see what's
happening there there
politically persecuting their own former
president Donald Trump he is the first
president in the entirety of U.S history
to face criminal charges
so this is a clear example of political
persecution of an opponent of a
political opponent
this is not something that happens in
democracies
and the U.S has a two-party state
just one step above
China or North Korea which are one party
States
um
and obviously it's so now it's now
abundantly clear that the Pentagon has
far more power than the White House
clearly Joe Biden is not running the
country the guy is not capable of of
running himself and Kamala Harris
obviously
is well rather incompetent
so clearly somebody else is running the
nation
and that is the Pentagon the defense
establishment which is the so-called
deep state
and so the U.S doesn't really believe in
democracy
the U.S has been propping up
dictatorships and autocracies across the
world because it suits them so it's all
so democracy is just a stick to beat
other nations with so I am not sure what
the agenda is it's just to keep up
appearances that we believe in democracy
we promote democracy and all that
nonsense
um
India I'm sure has been invited I'm sure
India will go go with it and play along
uh so I am not quite sure I've not
really looked into this this matter why
certain nations were not invited turkey
as we know is a part of NATO
Hungary
I believe is is reasonably closely
aligned with the US to a certain extent
um so I I don't quite know why they did
not invite turkey and Hungary because
maybe they believe that these two
nations are already reasonably closely
aligned with us perhaps maybe that could
be the the the the the thinking process
behind it perhaps
um Pakistan rejected the invitation
because they are anyway not a democracy
so yeah I don't know
all right
tanush says what are your personal
thoughts about conservative speakers
like Ben Shapiro Jordan Peterson and
what about lgbtq plus Q whatever gay
marriage in India all right
Ben Shapiro is is
like you say a conservative speaker in
the west so is Jordan Peterson Jordan
Peterson was like a few years ago he was
very very outspoken about uh
individual freedom and and uh
Traditional Values and all that but now
he has become very much aligned with the
agenda of the state itself
so I I don't take Jordan Peterson very
seriously if you watch some of his
earlier videos I had seen a few earlier
kind of it it kind of made sense some of
it was was
it kind of made sense but some things
have become very clear by now that he is
a Christian supremacist and a white
supremacist that's become very clear
he believes that the West is the
greatest civilization that ever existed
and the West gave everything that's good
to the world and without the West the
world would be in darkness and
Christianity is the best thing out there
and all these things so he's clearly a
Christian supremacist in the white
supremacist and a West supremacist yeah
Ben Shapiro I don't really follow him I
don't I haven't really paid a lot of
attention to him I think once again when
it comes to him
he obviously is is Jewish if I'm not
mistaken uh so I as far as I have seen
his his uh world view is also very much
Western Supremacy and when white
supremacy obviously there's a Jewish
angle Jews are not really white people
their ancestors were not white people so
some of it that is also there
but I don't think these people are real
role models for the world or especially
for anybody in India definitely not for
India uh what about lgbtq plus well it
exists then did it exist see India has
always been tolerant and
India has never ever persecuted lgbtq
people we we all know that certain small
maybe one or two percent of the human
population is like that so let it be let
them live their lives Live and Let Live
India has always been like that
gay marriage listen
I believe in progress
I believe that we have to respect uh
individual rights we have to respect
individual choices so if somebody is gay
or lgbtq or whatever it is we respect
that let them live their life they're
not hurting anybody they're not harming
anybody let their live their life in
whatever way they feel is best for them
we also have to respect civilization and
culture and tradition
right
we have to respect individual rights and
Liberty
we also have to respect every nation and
every culture's traditions
we have to respect both both things
there has to be a balance now in India's
civilization which is at least 10 000
years old have we ever had gay marriage
we haven't had that
so I would say that if gay people want
to live together let them live together
but there's no need for them to get or
maybe if they really seek marriage we
can have the court marriage or whatever
but it and and so
I I'm sure there's a lot of nuance in
context to all that I am absolutely in
favor of giving them the same rights and
the same respect as everybody else
when it comes to marriage I think I
think it's for the government to make
make a choice but it's definitely
something that Indian culture and
tradition has not had
so gay people never got they never had
the Dharma vivah or any such thing right
it was never it has never been part of
our culture so we obviously culture is a
living thing tradition is a living thing
new new cultural aspects emerge all the
time and New Traditions are formed
but I would say that we have to respect
what's what we have been doing in the
past ten thousand years
and I think gay marriage was never part
of Indian culture
gay persecution and oppression has never
been part of Indonesian culture never
ever it's we are the only culture that
has never persecuted gay people
for lgbtq what are people but we also
have never had gay marriage so I think
we need to find some kind of balance
between these two things I am absolutely
in favor of allowing of of giving the
same rights in same respect to the gay
people lgbtq people as everybody else
but let's not break our culture and
tradition for the sake of accommodating
Western perspectives that's what I would
say
so listen if if gay marriage is indeed
something that should happen perhaps let
it be the court marriage kind of thing
which would not have any religious angle
or cultural angle perhaps that that may
see I have not really spent a lot of
time thinking about this I'm thinking in
real time right now so maybe we need to
all come together Indian society and
culture
and people need to come together and
find some kind of consensus about this
the truth is that you know I'm not even
sure what the statistics are what
percentage of the world is lgbtq
historically it must it must have been
one or two percent but today this entire
ratio has been blown out of proportion
and everything in the U.S the US is a
weird Society
it is a sex obsessed Society everything
is about sex
you're the most important component of
your identity is your sexual orientation
why
so we need to
remember
that we don't have to start taking uh
you know
lead you know cues from the west and
start aping them
maybe it's fine for them maybe it's the
kind of society in religion and culture
they have it's all about everything is
it revolves around sex in India it's
never been like that so we need to
find Our Own Way Forward our own path
and we need not allow them to arm twist
us into changing our traditions and
culture and Society according to what
they think is right because that is
what's called cultural imperialism we
don't have to you know Bend to these
attempts to
to re-engineer Indian culture
okay
um
let us see what are the questions as I
can see
as I can see there are lots of questions
I I I I okay Pakistan okay we have not
have we taken any Pakistan questions
the question is should India attack
Pakistan and capture or Safeguard its
nuclear weapons
what will the world do in this case I
don't see the terrific Taliban Pakistan
taking control of Pakistan they can
certainly create chaos unleash chaos in
Pakistan but I don't see them in a being
able to take over Pakistan
uh
obviously like I have said in the past I
have nothing against the people of
Pakistan I wish them
prosperity and happiness and also the
children in future Generations but
Pakistan is a terrorist Nation it has to
be dismantled and that what needs to
happen is is that Pakistan needs to be
broken up into its components
Balochistan should become free
in Pakistan should come back to India
the shaks come Valley Etc should come
back to India
um
should
become free
Etc
that's what needs to happen now
obviously the question then is and this
would happen hopefully peacefully
without any War at all I don't want
India to waste its time getting into a
war there are there are other means of
getting of achieving what you want to
achieve the best way to win is to win
without fighting
the most Superior
kind of Victory is a victory that is
achieved without firing a single shot
that is the best form of victory
so that is what India should go for uh
attack attack we don't want any attacks
we want to be at peace we want to
achieve our objectives
very nicely without going to war and
that is certainly possible Pakistan is
on always on the brink of implosion
these days more than before
so I'm sure we can engineer something
hopefully peacefully without going to
war uh obviously that also gives us
raises the question as to what happens
to the Pakistani nuclear weapons so it
is something that's going to be India's
headache for sure India obviously the
Indian government must be
uh planning for such scenarios like plan
a plan B plan C that sort of thing or
maybe the Americans may also get
involved because
possibly some of the Pakistani nuclear
weapons could have some
U.S components perhaps possibly
or some U.S Technologies perhaps most
likely it's Chinese technology but who
knows so if there is some U.S aspect in
that the Americans may want to uh
secure those nukes before India does so
it's going to be a Race Against Time
When Pakistan implodes
so I I obviously it makes sense that the
Indian government must already have
wargamed all the possible scenarios as
to what happens when Pakistan implodes
or breaks up and
it will be something that needs to be
done as soon as possible to uh secure
those nukes
so I don't care what the world does in
that case Pakistan is India's headache
primarily secondary headache is for
Afghanistan in Iran but primarily it's
India's headache so it is I think going
to be for India to act First Act very
swiftly and secure those nuclear weapons
once the nukes are secured the rest we
can take care of in due in the due
course of time
yeah
is isro's new launch vehicle better than
SpaceX no
see the most powerful see currently what
does ISRO use we have the psrv the polar
space launch vehicle which is a
reasonably small rocket we have an even
smaller rocket which is something that
we're going to use for Rapid launches
the SSS LV or something like that small
space satellite launch vehicle or
something like that and then we have the
gslv which has a new name nowadays it is
the most powerful rocket that we have
the gslv Mark III or whatever it's
called these days it is a
not comparable to the best space SpaceX
Rockets which are way more powerful the
Falcon rocket in the new starship that
will soon be tested those are way more
powerful than isro's launch vehicles
so uh see I I am it's pretty clear that
we have excellent engineers and
scientists
and if you give them the go ahead they
can also start building much more
powerful Rockets we have the know-how we
have the technology
the motor the engine that we use for the
gslv
all you have to do is take 10 of those
put them together and build a bigger
rocket out of that it's it's as simple
as that obviously it's not as simple as
I make it sound it will it will entail
some engineering challenges but it's
something that we can do it's our
Engineers what our Engineers can
definitely do
so uh
it's a question of not getting the go
ahead from the government
so I think the Indian government does
not seem to have a lot of Ambitions
right now in the present day for ISRO
ISRO is being used as a well there's not
a lot of new researchers being done
so ISRO is being used to launch foreign
satellites and gain and earn some money
that's all
so it it's not
ideal
I would have hope that India would India
definitely in this Century needs to
become one of the top 203 space-faring
Nations
that is essential
because the two or three nations that
will lead the world in space exploration
in this Century are going to be the two
or three nations that lead the world in
everything
in all the other nations will be led and
controlled by the top two or three
nations
so India needs to be at the Forefront of
all these Technologies including space
exploration so right now it's not
happening we are still making do with
this gslv which is not really a very
powerful rocket it's the biggest and
most powerful rocket we have
but even the most powerful Chinese
Rockets are far more powerful than the
gslv the French Ariane is way more
powerful than the gslv
various I believe some Japanese Rockets
are more powerful than the gslv and the
NASA rockets and uh SpaceX Rockets are
way more powerful than India's gslv Mark
III so I think in two three years India
can develop a rocket that's 10 times
more powerful definitely into three
years we can do that
it's all about the government giving the
go ahead and giving the permission for
this to happen and obviously allocating
the funding
so these things are not happening right
now it's disappointing but it's
something that we can transform into
three years
if the government so decides
right let's see what else we have
um
let's see let's see
lots of questions
do we always have
armaan Singh says if India gets the
opportunity to join NATO which in recent
news we can hear will India join it can
it benefit us military-wise
so we have to understand what the full
scope of NATO is NATO is a U.S led
organization
it is owned by America it is not
portrayed that man in that manner but it
is an organization that is completely
controlled by the U.S and completely
owned by the us because it is the
Western European nations that make up
NATO and these are all American vasal
states in one way or the other
the Turks are kind of
on the on the
on the border on the boundary kind of
they have a quasi-independent foreign
policy but they also have U.S nuclear
weapons on their territory which is
control controlled by the Americans
obviously the French also have a kind of
Quasi independent foreign policy but
they are in no position to uh
to not exceed to the core demands of the
US
so NATO is all about being controlled by
the Americans
okay and all of these nations their
militaries come under the NATO command
on the another top NATO Commander at
certain point in time may be a
non-american but overall it's under U.S
control so if India joins NATO
hypothetically
India will have to agree to put India's
military under NATO command
do you think that will be acceptable to
any Indian person or to the Indian
government impossible
and there are other things that you have
to agree to
political things as well uh your nuclear
weapons may come under NATO command
and so on for instance you see
well nuclear weapons may not technically
come under NATO control the French have
a completely independent set of nukes
their nuclear weapons are deployed on
nuclear submarines which are always on
patrol
so that's what gives France their
nuclear deterrent the second strike
capability
the UK is nuclear weapons are
essentially
under U.S control
uh the UK has nucleus submarines but the
nuclear weapons the warheads are
placed on top of American missiles and I
am
sure that the red button the launch
button is not in Mr Richardson's hands
it's most likely in the pentagon's hands
so
uh so there's a lot of compromises that
you have to make if you become a part of
NATO your military comes under NATO
command and there will be other things
also which may be hidden you know Secret
uh certain secret set of conditions that
you may have to agree to so uh so I
don't think India should become a part
of NATO I don't think India will become
part of NATO India will cooperate
with NATO and the US on certain specific
issues
in those issues that are beneficial to
India's national interest
India will not become part of NATO as
far as I can see ever
India is part of the quad
which is not a military Alliance
officially
India
also engages with various other nations
in military cooperation so I don't see
NATO benefiting India military-wise it
may actually compromise India
from the military perspective because
India may have to put its Armed Forces
under
NATO command which essentially means us
command so if India gets the opportunity
India should say no India should say
that we will certainly cooperate with
you we will extend our cooperation to
you
based on what issue it is about issue
based cooperation but we will not become
a part of NATO and
subordinate our army and Military to
your command that won't happen
um
Dr Jay Shankar's supremacist says don't
you get pissed off by seeing the West is
now interfering in our internal politics
so much after Rahul Gandhi is being
disqualified and will not stand against
Modi ji in 2024 and 2029
the West has been interfering in the
entire world's internal matters
politics for decades
it's nothing new in India
certain you know
let's talk about
hypotheticals over here
there are various Nations
in which entire political parties have
been created which are
funded by the West
okay
I am not talking about India only over
here because I don't want people to say
that I'm pointing it
make pointing because at a certain
political party
but in various Nations it's happened
that suddenly some movement comes up in
a new political a bunch of new political
leaders come up who come out of nowhere
in a new political party is formed and
it is closely
linked with foreign funding
such things may or may not have a
husband perhaps in India also so this is
something that is a long-standing policy
of the West
and they also use ngos to affect
to to interfere in the internal matters
of nations in India we have more ngos
than schools and hospitals
and lots of these ngos receive money
from the west and maybe from other
places as well so that is another Avenue
of
of interfering in the internal matters
and politics of various Nations
so this is something everyone I'm not
sure if everyone knows this but the
people who matter in the government
definitely know this and
I'm sure they are keeping a very close
watch more than we realize on all these
activities
so listen you don't in geopolitics
emotions don't play a role so yeah you
may get angry or pissed off but that
really doesn't make any difference what
needs to happen is that the government
needs to find effect effective ways of
countering
these attempts
to interfere in the internal matters of
our nation
and you can't counter all of them thus
far you can do it only when you are
powerful enough so
before 2010 there was a lot of U.S
interference in China as well lots of
Chinese Communist Party officials were
compromised if you understand the
meaning of compromised
then after Mr Xi Jinping came to power
those
uh Western agents in the Chinese
Communist Party were dealt with very
harshly if you know what I mean
so when you rise to a certain level of
power and you become powerful enough you
can take stronger measures
to clean up
the internal system
and to deal with those who are
agents of foreign powers who are acting
against the national interest of your
nation
so it will happen in due time
right now India is not that powerful
India is a 3.5 or so trillion dollar
economy we need to First reach 10
trillion dollars of the 10 trillion
dollar Mark once we reach that we're
going to be way more powerful and we'll
be able to push back harder against
Western interference in India and other
interface as well it's not just the West
that's interfering other powers
including China will also be interfering
in India's politics so it's just a fact
of life there's no point getting pissed
off
either me or the government it's all
about the government taking the right
steps and I'm sure those steps are being
taken but they will not be publicized
obviously it's for not it's not for us
to know these things are kept secret so
that no one knows about it
all right let's take one or two more
questions
uh
my views on India building a satellite
City in Vladivostok so India has I think
said or proposed
to build a satellite City or something
like that in the Far East of Russia do
we know where Vladivostok is it's right
North
of North Korea
so you go to the Far East you know where
India is right so let's go eastwards
eastwards this towards you we know where
South Korea is and then you have North
Korea
and north of North Korea we have
Vladivostok
the great Port of Vladivostok
in the Russian Far East which is just a
few kilometers from North Korea if you
see the distance from there was talked
to North Korea the Border
it is about
132 kilometers 130 kilometers roughly
not really far away at all
so Russia will definitely welcome any
kind of investment activities from India
because India is in no way a threat for
Russia and India and Russia have an
excellent relationship a very
fruitful and warm relationship and
Russia has also already said in just a
couple of days ago that it wants to
strengthen that relationship with India
further India and China are the two
Nations Russia wants to work the most
closely with
so if India has proposed building a city
of some kind Satellite City or whatever
it is in this region the Russians will
definitely welcome it very much and
obviously if India is doing it it will
also benefit India in some way so it
will maybe be an Indian Outpost that
serves Russia and India as well from the
perspective of trade and uh other things
whatever they are
so I think it's good I think India
should do that you know hopefully it
will benefit India also substantially
and Russia as well so it's called a
win-win relationship so I think it's a
great thing
and I'm I'm glad to see India being more
proactive now for about two decades
there was this this policy of of look
East well looking is a passive thing you
can keep looking all day it will not
change the world but act East is acting
when you act you actually start changing
the world so India seems to be now
actually acting East recently India has
sold
missiles to
which nation was it the Philippines
and India may be selling
sorry it was Vietnam was it Philippines
Philippines most likely so that is
acting East India is actually acting
there India may also sell these brahmos
missiles to other nations in the in the
champasi South China Sea region which is
again very strong action and if India
builds a port or a or a satellite City
near Vladivostok it's going to be
something that benefits India as well
and Russia as well so it's good so India
is now finally beginning to get its act
together and India is now acting India
is now acting East which is great to see
so I think it's a very good and positive
and and good development something that
we should welcome very much
rajat says what is the scope of
blockchain technology is a career in it
worth pursuing see blockchain is the
decentralized Internet it's it's
blockchain technology the scope is is I
think it's great
uh so we all know about cryptocurrency
we know all know about Bitcoin right all
of this is built on top of the
blockchain the blockchain is something
that cannot be it is completely
decentralized it's not owned by anybody
it's not owned by any government so if
you have assets on the blockchain those
are gonna be those are not gonna be cut
off by or censored by the government
if you have a genuine cryptocurrency
that is truly decentralized like Bitcoin
for instance then uh
it's not controlled by any government so
let's say you you have a million okay
let's let's say hypothetically you have
a million US dollars
in a bank in the US and the U.S can
cut off your access to it
so if they close or freeze your bank
account then there's nothing you can do
about it and you lose all the money but
if you have
the same amount of money in Bitcoin on
the blockchain then no Government Can
can cut off your access to it and you
can use it in transactions for
transactions worldwide so blockchain
that's just one example of that then you
have non-fungible tokens uh
nfts which kind of are a fad right now
but eventually they will have a lot of
real world utility
so there's a lot of development that
will happen in that as well I think
blockchain could and eventually you will
have digital currencies you have
something called ethereum which is not
really decentralized because it is all
owned by one company or it's in one
place it's not truly decentralized but I
think blockchain has a huge amount of
potential
it can it is essentially permissionless
and it is truly decentralized nobody
actually owns it and a lot of
development can be done on top of that
you can have entire websites entire you
know uh tokens uh you can have
agreements that are
uh that that uh can live on the
blockchain I think there's a lot of
scope in that I think I think uh it's
not really
been uh exploited a lot thus far so I
think it's a career that is definitely
worth pursuing
most likely it's not a fad
cryptocurrencies have come and gone
two years ago everybody was into crypto
then the Bitcoin crashed and all that
but I think the the concept is an
excellent concept the blockchain concept
is also an excellent concept I think it
is something that will most likely stand
the test of time
so there are times when interest is high
and there are times when interest is low
but if something is going to withstand
the the test of time then even if
interest may be low right now in five
years time 10 years time it's gonna be
very valuable I think blockchain is
something that will be here to stay it
is web 3.0 the next iteration the
decentralized web so I think it is a
career definitely that's worth pursuing
okay I think we will take one more
question and then we will be done we've
already crossed way past
two hours
um
Michelle says though you didn't pick my
question thanks for answering another
one on the same topic okay I'm not sure
I have so many questions here but anyway
I'm glad I answered the question on the
same topic
um
when will I contest in KBC yes I want
one crore rupees I will contest should I
one crore rupees
um
okay let's take one more question
[Music]
akashas if you eat do you eat one meal a
day yes these are the meeting one meal a
day you know that's ideally what I want
to keep on doing one meal a day see
typically if you are a reasonably less
active person like everybody else is
these these days then you need
approximately 2000 calories in one day
and it's definitely possible to eat that
in one meal especially if you're a big
person so I
prefer to eat one meal a day just one
meal and be done with it then the rest
of the day you're free you don't have to
think about food
um
so it's called one minute omad
now I'm not always able to stick to that
yeah but that's something I prefer to do
what I don't have any specific recipes
what I do is I need a certain amount of
protein per day
that will come from a protein source and
the rest of it is just lightly fried
vegetables lots of vegetables or a soup
with vegetables
so most of the calories will come from
the protein and the fat in the protein
source
an example is paneer
yeah so if you want and and sometimes I
take whey protein if I'm if I'm working
out regularly
so I I want about 100 to 150 grams of
protein something in between that per
day and the rest of the calories can
from come from roasted vegetables or
stir-fried vegetables or something which
will be stir fried in typically in ghee
so that's what I do there's no specific
recipe I think it's a great lifestyle to
have you get all your calories from just
one meal the body adapts to that it's
not going to have any bad effects and it
kind of keeps your glucose level and all
that the insulin insulin levels and all
that down it gives you mental Clarity
fasting also helps I've done fast in the
past significant fast scary fasts all
that so yeah go ahead and do that Omar
thing and all the best with it so with
that we are done with today's session
two hours ten minutes thank you very
much for all the questions tomorrow we
will have the next episode of the Oscar
Bill show
in which I will take questions from from
the comments that you have put
in various parts of the YouTube channel
so thank you very much and I will see
you very soon in less than 24 hours time
until then take care
good night